Ashish Panigrahi

https://ashishpanigrahi.me

■ ashish.panigrahi@niser.ac.in • • paniash • in ashish-panigrahi99

About me

I am a 4^{th} year physics student studying at the **National Institute of Science Education and Research**, **Bhubaneswar**, **India**. My interests lie in the experimental aspects of quantum technologies including quantum optics/photonics, cavity QED and quantum information processing.

Nationality: Indian

Education

• National Institute of Science Education and Research (NISER) Integrated Master's (CGPA till 7th semester: 9.16/10.0) Bhubaneswar, India 2018 - 2023

- Major in physics with a minor in computer science.
- Relevant coursework: Quantum Mechanics, Classical Mechanics, Statistical Mechanics, Electromagnetism, Mathematical Methods, Condensed Matter Physics, Quantum Optics, Quantum information and computation, Experimental Techniques.
- Maharishi Vidya Mandir Senior Sec. School All India Senior Secondary Certificate Examination (CBSE) - 95.6%

Chennai, India May 2018

• PSG Public School
All India Secondary School Examination (CBSE) - CGPA 10

Coimbatore, India *May 2016*

Honors/Awards

• IBM Qiskit Advocate

2021

IBM Quantum

- Selected from a pool of global applicants.
- This achievement depicts a deep level of understanding with Qiskit including circuits, algorithms, simulators, qubits and noise.
- Through my contributions to the Qiskit and the quantum community, I have demonstrated an ability and commitment to educate and influence others by sharing ideas, knowledge and expertise in the field of quantum computing.

• **Zonal topper**Mimamsa 2021

IISER Pune

- Science quiz competition for undergraduates with participations from universities all over the country.
- Our team became the zonal topper for the *Odisha and Paschim Medinipur district* (WB) zone.
- National Graduate Physics Examination (National topper) Indian Association of Physics Teachers

2020

- Secured a score within the top 118 students among 12,000 candidates in the country.
- **Department Topper** $(1^{st} \& 2^{nd} year)$ School of Physical Sciences, NISER

2018-2020

• Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana Indian Institute of Science 2017

Bengaluru, India

 A prestigious fellowship program funded by the Department of Science and Technology of the Government of India.

• National Talent Search Examination

2016

National Council of Education Research and Training

New Delhi, India

- A national level scholarship program offered by the Government of India.
- It is one of the oldest and most prestigious scholarship programmes in the country.

Academic exposure

Qiskit Global Summer School

Virtual

IBM Quantum

July-August 2020

- An intensive 2 week virtual summer school on quantum computation and designing quantum circuits and algorithms using Qiskit.
- Did hands-on coding exercises to learn various quantum algorithms, pulse level control of qubits and concepts in quantum chemistry.
- Also did a project on simulating the ground energy level of LiH molecule using quantum variational eigensolver.

• National Initiative on Undergraduate Science (Physics)

Mumbai, Maharashtra *June* 2019

Homi Bhabha Centre for Science Education, TIFR

- Selected as one of top 70 students in the country to participate in this camp.
- An extensive 12-day course containing lectures, independent lab work and a field trip for 2 days.
- Lecture series on quantum mechanics, quantum information theory and quantum computation, basic condensed matter physics, many body physics, astronomy and astrophysics.
- About 30 hours of independent lab work.

Project experience

• Sixth Semester Project

Bhubaneswar, India

April - July 2021

Superconducting spintronics group, NISER

- Project guide: Dr. Kartik Senapati, Reader-F, NISER
- Worked on a semester project on the topic, "Study of spin current in NM/HM bilayer and trilayer systems".
- The goal was to be able to detect spin current via a bilayer system involving Cu and Pt, using the method of electrical detection.
- Through the project, I obtained hands on experience with experimental techniques such as magnetron sputtering and focused ion beam.

• Software Developer Internship

Australia

Quantum Brilliance

February - April 2021

- Project guide: Dr. Nariman Saadatmand, QBQE Product Manager
- Worked on QB's quantum emulator (QBQE) and enhanced functionality of its QAOA module using C++.

• Summer Project

Bhubaneswar, India

May - June 2019

Institute of Physics, Bhubaneswar

- Project guide: Dr. Debakanta Samal, Reader-F, Institute of Physics
- Reading project on "Study on anisotropic magnetoresistance".
- Topics covered: Origin of magnetoresistance, theory of magnetoresistance in real metals using the 2-band charge carrier model, origin of anisotropic magnetoresistance, its applications and current research scenario in the field.

Open-source contributions

• Qiskit Textbook GitHub

Learn Quantum Computation using Qiskit

April 2020 - Present

- Qiskit is IBM's software development kit for building software to interact with IBM's quantum devices and OpenQASM.
- The textbook is equivalent to a university level course for learning quantum computation and beyond.
- I am a collaborator for this project and have actively contributed with over 50+ commits since April 2020.

Licenses & Certifications

• IBM Certified Associate Developer

IBM

Quantum Computation using Qiskit v0.2X

July 2021

- This certification demonstrates fundamental knowledge of quantum computing concepts and the ability to express them using the Qiskit open source software development kit (SDK).
- Shows experience in using the Qiskit SDK from the Python programming language to create and execute quantum computing programs on IBM Quantum computers and simulators.

• Introduction to Quantum Computing Course

Qubit by Qubit

IBM Quantum & The Coding School

October 2020 - May 2021

 Developed a foundational understanding of quantum computing, with topics including introductory linear algebra, coding with Qiskit, quantum mechanics, quantum algorithms, and quantum applications.

• Challenge Fall 2020 Achievement - Intermediate

IBM

IBM Quantum

December 2020

- Demonstrated an ability to implement near-future quantum data structures and design a quantum game solver using Grover's algorithm.
- Showed an understanding of quantum circuits, the gates that comprise such circuits, Grover's algorithm, and qRAM (quantum random access memory) as a way to implement complex data structures.

• CS-191x: Quantum Mechanics and Quantum Computation

edX

University of California, Berkeley

August 2020

- Coursework involved ranging from the basics of the qubit to quantum algorithms such as Grover's, Shor's etc. to the Bloch sphere and Schrödinger's wave equation.
- Final score: 97%

Volunteering

• Project Lovelace

Scientific programming problems

May 2021 - Present

- Project Lovelace is a platform to learn science through programming.
- Member of the team to add new problems and maintain the website (both frontend and backend).
- Website: https://projectlovelace.net

• Full-Stack Quantum Computation

Community-driven, open-source education resources

December 2020 - Present

- Part of the team as a curator of various articles on quantum technologies, submitted by volunteers.
- Website: https://fullstackquantumcomputation.tech

Dung and

Avanti Fellows NGO

- Duties included mentoring students from grades 11 and 12.
- My weekend work involved having a one-to-one discussion with students on physics and general advice on entrance exams.

Technical skills

Programming and scripting languages

Julia, C, C++, Bash, and Python (Libraries: *Scipy, Numpy, Matplotlib, Sympy*)

Markup languages

LATEX, Markdown, Groff, HTML

Quantum Frameworks

Qiskit, QuTiP, PennyLane

General computing tools

Vim, git, tmux, gnuplot

